[Music]
yesterday, December 7th,
1941. A date which will live in infamy.
[Music]
The United States of America was
suddenly and deliberately attacked by
naval and air forces of the Empire of
[Music]
Japan. that the Congress declare that
since the unprovoked and desperately
attacked by Japan, a state of war has
existed between the United States and
the Japanese Empire.
Pearl Harbor came as a complete shock to
some, but an inevitable reality for
others, with this surprise attack
marking the United States entry into the
deadliest war in human history, in which
over 50 million people would perish
across the globe. But why did the
Japanese attack Pearl Harbor? What were
their motivations? And how did they
manage to catch the Americans so offg
guard with their attack on Pearl Harbor
becoming the deadliest attack on US
territory until the events of
9/11? For the United States, a series of
decisions made by both Roosevelt himself
and others in the State Department were
instrumental in bringing about Japan's
attack with often well-intentioned
policies aimed at stopping the spread of
the Japanese Empire in Asia, ultimately
bringing war upon their own soldiers
stationed overseas. To understand the
real reason Japan attacked Pearl Harbor,
the video will be split into four
distinct chapters, each highlighting the
key reasons as to why it occurred. The
first chapter will highlight Japan's
rapid transformation from an isolated
country at the time of the samurai into
a modern industrial power, one that
became so powerful in such a short time
that it could even rival the great
colonial nations of the West. Having
modernized the nation during the Maji
restoration, chapter 2 will discuss what
they did with this newfound wealth and
power, taking you step by step through
Japan's wars of conquest in East Asia,
which ultimately put them on the road to
war with the United States. This chapter
will also explore the challenges Japan
faced during the early 20th century as
it tackled a growing empire and suffered
under the economic turmoil of the Great
Depression. Ultimately, this would lead
to the growth of fanaticism and the
concentration of military power across
Japanese society, making a conflict with
the West all but inevitable. The third
chapter will take you step by step
through the negotiations between Japan
and the United States, so you can hear
what each side said in their own words
during the critical months leading up to
Pearl Harbor. We will also explore how
leaders on both sides managed the
situation, the compromises they reached,
and finally the real reasons why
negotiations broke down. In the last and
final chapter, we will take you through
the assault on Pearl Harbor itself,
including the detailed plans of Israu
Yamamoto, the mastermind behind the
attack, and why he chose this base on
the island's chain of Hawaii in the
middle of the Pacific as the primary
target for his attack. Join us as we
take you step by step and chapter by
chapter through the actual reasons Japan
attacked Pearl Harbor and how the United
States was drawn into the most deadly
conflict in human history.
[Music]
Japan, an island nation on the edge of
the Asian continent, had never been the
richest or most dominant nation in the
region. Its mountainous terrain limited
agriculture. It lacked the vital raw
materials required for industrialization
and for centuries was ruled over by a
series of warlords who kept Japan
isolated from the rest of the world. So
how was it that this island nation
managed to conquer 20% of the world's
population and go head-to-head against
the world's rising superpower, the
United States? Just a century before
Pearl Harbor, Japan was an isolationist
nation with virtually no contact with
the rest of the world. But that was soon
to change. In the late 18th century,
Great Britain had become the first
nation in the world to industrialize
with its steam engine, power looms, and
the mass production of steel,
revolutionizing the fields of
transportation, manufacturing, and
warfare. By the mid-9th century, the
industrial revolution had swept across
Western Europe with the new wealth and
technology they now possessed, fueling
the rapid expansion of colonial empires
across the globe. What would emerge
would now be a growing divide between
these western superpowers and the rest
of the world with traditional societies
like the Japanese suddenly unable to
defend themselves in the face of such an
overwhelming technological gap.
Japan ruled over by a series of powerful
warlords known as Shogun had kept the
country almost completely isolated for
centuries with only limited forms of
trade happening with the Chinese and
Dutch. But in 1852, American President
Milard Filillmore, wanting to expand
trade in the east, would send four armed
steel warships to the shores of Japan,
demanding that their ports be opened to
American ships and that the United
States be given a permanent diplomatic
presence in the country. Under the
command of Commodore Matthew C. Perry,
the American ships would enter Ido Bay,
Japan's principal harbor. With their
sheer size, advanced weaponry, and
ability to move under their own power,
far beyond anything Japan had seen
before, sparking fear and anxiety
throughout the nation. The Japanese
would refer to these ships as Cororafun
or black ships, with their arrival
symbolizing the end of Japan's
200-year-old policy of sukoku or
seclusion. Being forced to accept these
American terms under the threat of
violence, the Japanese agreed to open
its ports and were made to sign a series
of unequal treaties that benefited the
US to their own detriment. Japan was
powerless. All they could do was accept
the terms with them having no feasible
way of defeating a country with such
advanced technology.
The realities of globalization, however,
would not just hit Japan with China
providing a warning to all nations in
the east of what was to happen if they
failed to modernize and accept the
realities of the new world they now
found themselves in. the cultural and
economic center of the Asian world for
the past 2,000 years, China was entering
a period of total chaos. Plagued by a
series of devastating civil wars with
the Taiping Rebellion alone leading to
the deaths of nearly 30 million people.
The ruiningQing dynasty was slowly
losing its grip on power with the nation
becoming increasingly destabilized.
Seeing this, industrial powers from the
west would look to exploit China's
weakened state. The British East India
Company wanting to sell more goods in
the East flooded China with opium
causing widespread addiction across the
Chinese population. When theQing
government attempted to halt this trade,
however, Britain along with France waged
two wars to protect their economic
interests, both of which China would
lose. These conflicts, known as the Opia
Wars, demonstrated to the East for the
first time the overwhelming
technological and military advantages of
the industrialized European powers. As a
result, the Chinese, just like Japan,
were forced to sign a series of unequal
treaties that not only now legalized
opium across the country, but also
granted Western powers favorable trade
concessions, reparations, and
territorial rights, with Hong Kong being
handed over to the British Empire,
ushering in a period known to the
Chinese as the century of humiliation.
Not only this, but to the north, Russia,
too, would look to capitalize upon
China's weakness, securing significant
territorial gains at their expense,
including a 3,000-mi stretch of
coastline along the Pacific Ocean,
establishing Russia as a major power in
Asia and a dominant force in the
Pacific. For the Japanese, the Americans
had landed on their shores. The European
powers were dictating terms to China,
and Russia was gaining massive sways of
territory in the north. It was clear if
they were to protect themselves and find
their place in this new global order,
Japan needed to study what had made the
West so
powerful. For the Japanese, China would
also provide an example of what not to
do when facing the threats of the new
industrialized world. Viewing Western
civilization as barbaric and their own
culture as superior, China's leaders
underestimated the danger they now faced
and instead of trying to understand
their enemy, simply employed the same
military techniques they had done for
centuries. As author Sarah C. Payne
describes it, Chinese elite pervasive
contempt for foreigners had discouraged
the study of the West. They failed to
appreciate the unprecedented nature of
the threat, let alone the need to
counter with an unprecedented strategy.
The Chinese assumed what had functioned
so well in the past would do so in the
future. They were wrong. Watching these
events unfold in China and wanting to
avoid the same mistakes, Japanese
leaders began a serious effort to study
the West, hoping to understand what made
these new world powers so successful so
that they could emulate it for
themselves. The study of the West began
in 1857, which initially saw the mass
translation of Western books into
Japanese and then accelerated when
students were sent abroad to study
Western law, science, navigation, and
medicine. What would result would be a
new generation of reformers ready to
bring Japan into the industrial age. But
if any serious change was to happen,
then Japan's military overlords, the
Shogun, a symbol of tradition and
stagnation, would have to be abolished.
The shogunut's power and status had been
seriously weakened following its
inability to respond to Matthew Perry's
black ships and the unequal treaties
that followed with a revolution to
overthrow their rule beginning in 1868
known as the Bin War. After a decisive
defeat at the battle of Toba Fushimi,
Japan's last shogun, Tokagawa Yoshobu,
would resign with the shogunut system
officially coming to an end. In his
place, the reformers would put
15-year-old Emperor Magi in charge of
the country, who would serve as a
legitimizer of their new
regime, becoming known as the Maji
Reformers, this new government would
implement a series of sweeping reforms
aimed at the rapid modernization of the
country.
Moving the capital from Kyoto to Ido,
they would rename the city Tokyo,
meaning eastern capital, symbolizing a
new era for Japan. Soon, the government
was sending whole delegations of civil
servants abroad in which they would
study a wide range of Western
institutions trying to learn as much of
the new world as they could. The most
renowned of these was the Iwakura
mission led by prominent Maji reformer
Iwakura Tamomi. This delegation of 50
statesmen and scholars embarked on a
two-year journey across 12 countries
including Britain and the United States
where they met with influential figures
such as Queen Victoria and President
Ulyses Srant. Studying a whole array of
Western institutions and technological
developments. The Iakura mission would
come to the conclusion that simply
acquiring modern technology was not
enough. To truly thrive, Japan needed to
embrace the very foundations of Western
power. their civil, economic and
political institutions. These they
realized were the essential building
blocks for a new and thriving Japanese
society. Realizing that rapid
modernization required an educated
population, the Maji reformers would
make elementary education compulsory as
well as establishing Tokyo Imperial
University. Just 14 years later, a
British-style parliament was also
introduced. The diet, which would see a
cabinet serve under a prime minister
with a modern civil service, westernized
criminal code, and judicial system also
being established. A new constitution
was drafted in 1889 along with a whole
array of economic reforms with a central
bank, the Bank of Japan, being founded
in 1882 and Marinucci, a thriving
business district springing up in Tokyo
being nicknamed Little London due to its
rows of red brick buildings. Soon,
millions of people from across the
nation would leave the countryside and
flock to the cities, being employed in
various commercial and industrial
industries, with Tokyo becoming a
modern-day metropolis with its
population doubling to 2.2 million
people over the coming decades. These
reforms, however, would come at a cost.
The rapid shift towards a westernized
society disrupted traditional ways of
life, leading to discontent among many
who felt their cultural identity was
being eroded. As a result, the Maji
reformers would use Shinto, Japan's
traditional religion, to help bridge the
divide from the old to the new. Shinto
beliefs held that the emperor was a
divine figure descended from the sun
goddess Amitarasu. The Maji reformers,
therefore, would use the emperor's
divine and unquestioned status in order
to legitimize the creation of their new
government and the policies they would
now enact. As he was a divine figure,
the emperor demanded absolute loyalty
from every Japanese citizen. And as he
gave his blessing to the government,
this would give them the authority to
rule. Emperor Magi and his successors
would now be the social glue that held
the fabric of Japanese society together,
helping transform the nation from one of
Shogunut's rulers to the new Western
imperial system. However, these
institutions would not be the only thing
that Japanese leaders took from the
West. They also recognized that nearly
all the great powers of the time had
large empires with significant
militaries to support them and believed
that there was no reason that Japan
should not have this too in order to
protect their interests and gain status
as a regional power. Therefore, the Maji
reformers believed that a Japanese
empire would have to be created.
Conscription would be introduced in 1873
with the Japanese army undergoing rapid
modernization drawing heavily on the
Prussian model to forge a disciplined
and structured fighting force with the
samurai who had seen their place in
society disappear with the end of the
shogunut. Finding their role once again
by becoming the officers of the newly
formed Imperial Japanese Army. The Navy
too would undergo a massive
transformation as General Yamagata
Aritomo would advocate. Japan was to
become a floating fortress that was able
to exercise power in all directions. As
such, a new Japanese Navy was to be
established based off the British Navy,
the most powerful in the world at the
time, with a large fleet of over 30
modern warships under Japan's control by
the end of the century. What had begun
as an agricultural society ruled over by
shogunut warlords had now transformed
itself into a new world power with
western institutions, a thriving
economy, and a military capable of
defeating all those it fought against in
the region. The balance of power in East
Asia was about to undergo a radical
transformation. The path to war with the
United States had now begun.
[Music]
The instability China's civil wars had
ushered in, not only in China, but
across the region, had created a power
vacuum in which another great power
would look to fill its place. For the
Japanese, who were now looking to
establish a new empire across the Asian
continent, this presented a promising
opportunity. For centuries, Korea had
been a tributary state to China,
acknowledging its dominance in exchange
for protection. Japan, however, would
now seek to acquire control of Korea for
themselves. Not only would it provide a
perfect staging base for further
military expansion into East Asia, but a
decisive victory abroad would show those
at home who were still resistant to the
westernization of their country that the
Maji reforms were in fact working. Not
only this, but Japanese control over
Korea could help to stop Russian
expansionism, who were also looking to
capitalize upon China's weakness. In
1891, the Russian government decided to
build the Trans Siberian Railway that
would allow for the rapid transportation
of troops into the east, facilitating
the creation of a Russian Empire in
Asia, land that the Japanese had been
keen to take for themselves. Securing
Korea before the completion of the Trans
Siberian Railway was therefore crucial
for Japan, allowing Russia to expand
into the region would not only expose
Japan to potential invasions from the
mainland, but also hinder their
ambitions for territorial expansion.
Beginning the first SinoJapanese war in
1894, Japan invaded Korea, capturing
Korean King Gojong and forcing him to
install a puppet government subservient
to Japanese interests, defeating the
Chinese in almost every battle both at
land and sea. Japan would secure a
victory in just 8 months, taking Korea,
the island of Formosa, as well as the
Liao Dong Peninsula. With this territory
now under their control, Japan had made
the first steps towards creating their
new empire, establishing the nation as a
rising power in Asia. Japan's success,
however, would not be looked upon
favorably by the Russians, whose own
plans for an Asian empire were now under
threat. As a result, Russia would
leverage its relationships with Germany
and France with the three delivering an
ultimatum known as the triple
intervention, demanding under the threat
of force that Japan returned the Loaong
Peninsula to China, something they would
reluctantly agree to. The Japanese would
feel a deep sense of humiliation by the
forced withdrawal with nationalist
sentiments and the desire for revenge
growing throughout the nation. To make
matters worse, Russia would seize the
Laodong Peninsula for themselves just 3
years later. A clear betrayal that
signaled to the Japanese that the West
and in particular the Russians could not
be trusted. After so much progress had
been made by the Maji reformers, it was
clear they were still not respected on
the world stage and something would have
to be done. Japan would now embark on a
massive military buildup. If the Western
powers were to threaten them again, they
would have the resources necessary to
resist any foreign
[Music]
interference. With tensions growing
between Japan and Russia, both powers
would now look to the Chinese province
of Manuria as a target for expansion.
For the Russians, the acquisition of
land in the east was something the newar
Nicholas II believed could enhance his
prestige and legitimize his rule.
Seeking to assert their claim over
Manuria, Russia would begin to expand
the Trans Siberian Railway into the
province, laying down a thousand m of
track. For the Japanese, however,
Manuria wasn't just a vanity project
aimed to legitimize the rule of a new
leader. For them, it was an absolute
necessity to their national survival.
Not only was it a gateway to the rest of
Asia, but it was also rich in resources
such as coal, iron, and lumber, which
were essential for industrialization and
further military expansion. However,
unknown to both parties at the time, it
would yet again be developments in China
that would cause turmoil across the
region. Resenting their treatment at the
hands of the Western powers, a group of
Chinese rebels known as the Boxers would
stage an uprising aimed at expelling the
so-called foreign devils that they saw
as destroying their country. As part of
their rebellion, however, the Boxers
would target Russia's newly built and
highly expensive railway line in
Manuria, destroying much of the work
that had already been done. In response,
the Russians would launch a full-scale
invasion of the province in 1900,
completely occupying Manuria in order to
protect their interests. For the
Japanese, this was the worst case
scenario and a complete disaster. With
Russia having taken over the land they
had been so keen to take for themselves.
As the years went on, and with the
Russians refusing to withdraw, Japanese
leadership would see no other option but
to break off all diplomatic ties with
Russia in 1904. The only way to secure
control over Manuria would now be by
force. Launching a surprise torpedo
attack on the Russian fleet anchored at
Port Arthur. It would mark the beginning
of what would later be known as the
Russo-Japanese War. What would follow
would be a series of battles across
Korea and Manuria. With each side
sustaining heavy casualties throughout
the coming months, sending
reinforcements and with the British
denying them passage through the Suez
Canal, the Russian fleet would be forced
to sail around the coast of Africa. And
by the time they arrived in the Pacific
in 1905, the Japanese fleet was waiting
for them. Admiral Togo Heihhatiro,
commanding the Japanese forces, would
manage to achieve a decisive victory at
the Battle of Toshima, annihilating the
entire Russian fleet, and with it any
hopes of their victory. For one young
Japanese officer, Israu Yamamoto, the
Battle of Toshima would be a defining
moment. The 21-year-old, who would later
masterminded the attack on Pearl Harbor,
saw firsthand the devastating
consequences of Japan's initial surprise
attack against the Russian fleet, from
which they never fully recovered. This
victory achieved against a much larger
power showed the effectiveness of such
tactics, a lesson Yamamoto would revisit
decades later when he was tasked with
formulating a plan to attack the United
States. Completely humiliated, Russian
morale would collapse overnight with Zan
Nicholas being forced to sign the Treaty
of Portsmouth, granting Japan the
southern half of Sackelin Island as well
as control of the southern half of
Manuria that not only included its
mineral-rich land, but also the prized
Russian railway, the Zar had exerted so
much effort to keep. Japan's
militarization had worked. They had
fought a great European power and won,
gained the territory that they had hoped
for, and solidified Japan rather than
Russia as the new dominant power in
Asia. Not only this, but their victory
would mark the first time an Asian power
would defeat a European nation in the
modern age, a defining moment that
marked the rise of Japanese supremacy in
the
[Music]
East. Having established themselves as a
rising power on the world stage, the
Japanese were now beginning to be taken
seriously by the industrialized great
powers of the West and would further
enhance their prestige by fighting
alongside the Allied forces during the
First World War. Doing so would allow
them to seize and occupy German colonial
possessions across the region with
China's Shangdong province as well as
several island chains in the central
Pacific. The Maranas, the Marshalss, and
the Carolas all coming under Japanese
control. However, despite their best
efforts to be seen as equals on the
international stage, it was still
apparent to many Japanese that they were
looked down upon as inferior by the
Western powers. During the Versail peace
talks after the war, Japan's attempts to
introduce a racial equality clause were
shut down by the imperial powers as the
clause would have undermined their
justifications for colonial rule. Not
only this, but 6 years later in 1924, an
American law was passed preventing
immigration from Asia, effectively
banning all Japanese migration to the
United States. This law would leave no
doubt in Japanese minds that they were
subject to discriminatory treatment by
the west and it made clear that they
would never be seen as equal
[Music]
partners. From the American perspective,
Japan's successful imperial conquests in
Asia was a threat to both their security
and economic interests in the region.
Following their victory in the
SpanishAmerican War of 1898, the United
States had established itself as a major
power in the Pacific, gaining control
over the former Spanish colonies of Guam
and the Philippines. To safeguard its
newfound strategic and economic
interests in the region, the United
States adopted an open door policy
towards China, aimed at protecting
Chinese sovereignty. As China
represented the biggest potential market
in the east, making sure this market
remained open would be one of America's
top priorities. To achieve this, they
would look to implement a series of
treaties to prevent any one nation and
in particular Japan from taking over the
region. In these treaties, the United
States, Japan, and a number of other
European powers, placed limitations on
the number of battleships and battle
cruisers each nation could possess,
prohibited the construction of new
military bases in the Pacific, agreed to
not invade one another's territories,
and most importantly, that all nations
involved would uphold China's
territorial sovereignty and grant each
other equal access to the Chinese
market. However, as a result of these
treaties, Japan had been forced to
return the Shangdong province to China,
a prize they had only just gained due to
their participation during World War I.
Acceptance of these terms would spark
outrage amongst Japanese nationalists
who saw these treaties as yet another
example of unwanted Western
interference. As a result, they decided
to take action into their own hands,
assassinating Japanese Prime Minister
Tekashihara, the most prominent advocate
of the new treaties. This assassination
marked a growing rise in Japanese
nationalism with hardline militarists
coming to play an increasingly important
role as Japan transitioned into the
modern era.
Although Japan had transitioned away
from the shogunut system of the 19th
century, the militaristic culture it
left behind remained deeply ingrained
within Japanese society. The Maji
generation who had ushered in
westernstyle government were now
reaching their end of their lives with
the idea that the military be
subordinates to the government fading
away with them. With their passing and
Japan's many imperial victories across
Asia and the Pacific, a growing
nationalist sentiment would emerge in
their place. With the military gaining
ever more fame, prestige, and public
support for the politicians who worked
to steer Japan through international
politics, they were beginning to face
growing public disapproval with every
western demand that they capitulated to.
With each being perceived as a national
humiliation, eroding their public image
and fueling discontent. As such, the
void the Maji generation had left in
government would soon be filled with
fanatical militarists, and by the early
1920s, the military had gained enough
power to bypass the prime minister
completely, pledging their allegiance
only to the emperor himself. The system
that would emerge would come to be known
as state Shinto, where a strong
centralized government under the
leadership of a divine emperor was used
to justify militaristic expansion. A key
figure in the development of Shinto
ultraationalism was political
philosopher Yu Sugi Shinki who argued
that Japan as the embodiment of divine
will had not only a right but a duty to
spread its superior culture and
civilization to other parts of Asia. It
was an ideology that was to take grip of
Japan's ruling military elite coming to
full fruition under the reign of Emperor
Hirohito, the grandson of Emperor Magi,
who ascended to the throne in 1926.
Little did Hiito know that as soon as he
came to power, Japan would be thrust
into a new age, one marked by a rapid
transformation of its economy, culture,
and military. Changes just as big as his
grandfather, Emperor Magi, had faced all
those years
[Music]
ago. In 1929, the New York Stock
Exchange, the largest in the world, was
hit with a stock market crash, losing
90% of its value over the next 3 years.
Alongside this, people began to lose
faith in the entire financial system,
looking to withdraw their deposits. As a
result, a run on the banks occurred, and
when the majority of their customers
came to withdraw their funds, the banks
collapsed, wiping out nearly a third of
the money supply and people's savings
across the nation. In 1930, in an
attempt to rekindle the economy,
President Herbert Hoover signed the
Smoot Hornley Tariff Act that taxed
foreign imports when they entered the
United States. However, instead of
alleviating the situation, what resulted
was an all-out global trade war with
high taxes being placed on American
goods around the world in retaliation.
As a result, American exports tanked and
unemployment rose to nearly 25% with
factories, farms, and other industries
now laying off workers as there was
dwindling demand for their products.
Soon this international trade war that
the Smoot Holy tariffs had started had
turned into a global depression with
high unemployment, widespread poverty,
and the destruction of industry
affecting nearly every country on the
planet. Japan would be hit especially
hard as its economy revolved around
exporting goods to the United States and
other foreign nations. With these
foreign markets having now disappeared,
Japanese exports were cut in half almost
overnight with rising unemployment and
social unrest emerging across the
country. Japan's silk industry, one of
its principal exports to the United
States, dropped by almost 80%, causing
widespread hardship across the
countryside with protests and
demonstrations against the government
becoming the norm. Many felt betrayed by
their leaders and increasingly looked to
the military for solutions. Much like in
Germany, where the economic turmoil of
the Weimar Republic had led to the rise
of authoritarian leadership, who
promised salvation through territorial
expansion, the same would now occur in
Japan. The military would use the
economic crisis to further bolster their
position, advocating that it was vital
that Japan secure more resources and
territory in Asia in order to become
economically self-sufficient. To free
themselves from the reliance on western
trade, they argued they would need to
conquer new territory with the people in
this land, providing them with new
markets to export their products to, as
well as the raw materials needed to fuel
their industry, as they had done in the
past. The target for this expansion
would be in China, with Japanese
militarists now looking to complete
their takeover of the resourcerich
province of Manuria. This target,
however, would set them on the path of
no return. From here on out, the road to
the Second World War had
[Music]
begun. With economic turmoil gripping
the country and extreme politics on the
rise, many would now turn to the
military's policy of territorial
expansion as a way to secure the
necessary resources and markets needed
to alleviate Japan's domestic situation.
Soon a number of secret organizations
would emerge throughout the military
comprised of junior officers who had
been completely indoctrinated in the
tenants of state Shinto believing in
Japan's racial and cultural superiority
over the other peoples of Asia and saw a
policy of aggressive expansionism as the
only route to their nation's prosperity.
Known collectively as the young
officers, they would follow in a
centuries old Japanese tradition known
as gay cockujo, in which junior officers
would frequently disobey the orders
handed down to them and instead take
matters into their own hands. Such ideas
had infiltrated Japan's force stationed
in southern Manuria known as the
Quantang Army, with many coming to
believe that their superiors were being
too slow to act and that an immediate
takeover of the entirety of Manuria
along with the wealth of materials it
contained was the only way to ensure
Japan's prosperity. And so on the
evening of September 18th, 1931,
Japanese Quantang soldiers would blow up
a section of their own South Manurion
railway, which served as a vital
transportation route for resources and
troops in the province, falsely blaming
the incident on the Chinese rebels. The
Quantang army would use it as an excuse
to launch a full-scale invasion of
Manuria. Although the Japanese
government opposed the attack, there was
little they could do as the QuanTang
officers simply ignored their demands to
stop the assault with the politicians
ultimately having to give the campaign
their blessing in order to save face and
make it seem like they were still in
control. Completing the occupation of
Manuria by the start of 1932, the
Japanese would rename the region Manchu
Quo, a puppet state that would now serve
their interests. The attack would be
seen as an unacceptable act of Japanese
aggression in the West with the League
of Nations, a new international
peacekeeping organization founded after
World War I, responding to Chinese pleas
for help by demanding Japan's withdrawal
from the region. However, the United
States at this point was still not a
member of the League with their absence
meaning that the institution lacked the
military power and political influence
needed to have a significant effect upon
Japan's actions. As a result, Japan
simply refused to comply with the League
suggestions and left the institution in
1933.
Japan,
however, find it impossible to accept
the report adopted by the assembly.
The Japanese delegates refuse to accept
the decision and sensationally walk out
of the assembly. A fateful step.
With this act, Japan had further
isolated itself from international
politics with the weakness the League of
Nations had displayed, emboldening them
to pursue even more military conquests.
Having secured their interests in
Manuria, the young officers would come
to play an increasingly significant role
over the coming years, launching a wave
of political assassinations that would
forever change Japan, killing prime
ministers, business leaders, and any who
they saw as holding Japan back from a
policy of unrestricted military
expansion. As one of the young officers
would state when on trial for the murder
of Prime Minister Inu Kai Koshi, the
imperial way should be spread through
the world. The Asiatic nations being
first consolidated into a unit and
thereafter the rest of the world. The
military's grip on Japan had been
secured. From here on out, they would be
the ones that would decide the fate of
the
nation. By 1937, the military's control
over Japan was absolute. The government
was packed with Shinto loyalists and
their invasion of Manuria had been an
unprecedented success. Heavily investing
in infrastructure, the Japanese would
rapidly expand the railway and road
systems across their newly formed puppet
state, invest in education, and poured
money into the development of heavy
industry that would provide the raw
materials needed to sustain their
empire. By 1943, Japan had transformed
Manuria from an impoverished
agricultural society plagued by civil
wars into an economic powerhouse with
their newly founded puppet state
producing 50% of all Chinese coal, 78%
of its electricity, 87% of its pig iron,
93% of its steel, 66% of its concrete,
and 99% of its oil. By 1945, it had a
per capita income 50% higher than the
rest of China and had become the most
industrialized part of Asia outside the
Japanese home islands, outproducing even
Shanghai and the Yangze River Valley,
long the heart of China's modern
economy. Such a success was not
overlooked by Japan's ruling military
elite who would take this as a
confirmation that their plan to revive
Japan's economy through conquest was in
fact correct and that further expansion
into China was now required if they were
to continue to fuel their growing
empire. The opportunity to do so would
present itself in July 1937 when a
seemingly minor border clash known as
the Marco Polo Bridge incident ignited a
full-scale war between China and Japan.
Japanese commanders believed that the
conflict would be resolved within a
matter of months, expecting that the
Chinese, as they had done during the
invasion of Manuria, would quickly come
to a settlement rather than risk allout
war. The Chinese, however, had come to
see the Japanese as an existential
threat to the survival of their country,
who would not stop until the entirety of
China came under their control. Agreeing
to halt the civil war that had plagued
China for the last 10 years, the leaders
of the nation's two most significant
parties, Chiang Kaishek of the Quoming
Tang and Maoadong of the Chinese
Communist Party, would put aside their
differences to form a united front
against Japan. With them now united into
one force, the Japanese would face more
resistance than they ever had before.
With Japan committing over 600,000 men
by the end of 1937, with the number soon
rising to over a million men just a year
later, the conflict known as the Second
SinoJapanese War would become the
central focus for Japan over the next 8
years, only coming to an end with
Japan's defeat at the end of the Second
World War. By the end of 1937, in just 6
months, Japanese forces had managed to
take nearly all of China's major cities,
with them then marching west from
Shanghai towards the city of Nanking.
Here, however, the Japanese would put
their fanaticism on full display,
committing one of the most brutal acts
in the history of warfare. By December,
50,000 Japanese troops had reached the
city who would participate in the
destruction, widespread slaughter, rape,
and murder of innocent civilians.
300,000 lives, half of the city's
population, would be taken in less than
6 weeks, most being buried in mass
graves with their hands tied behind
their backs. Further atrocities would
follow with the Japanese setting up
mobile brothel and kidnapping women from
China and Korea, who would be forced
against their will to serve the needs of
the Japanese soldiers. Up to 400,000 of
what would later be known as comfort
women are estimated to have been taken
into captivity. With the news of such
atrocities quickly reaching the west in
America, reports of Japanese brutality
would cause widespread condemnation with
Congress ultimately choosing to provide
China with loans, arms, and supplies to
help in their struggle against Japan and
to maintain their open door policy in
the region. For American leaders,
although they wish to avoid a direct war
with Japan for the time being, there was
now no question that they were to be
viewed as an enemy, not just to America
itself, but to the international order.
they were trying to uphold. By 1939, the
Japanese occupied 1/3 of China with most
of its modern industry, raw materials,
railroads, and cities now directly under
their control. But despite their rapid
conquest of the region, they had
embarked on a campaign that was simply
far more difficult than anything they
had imagined. Bogged down in the
countryside, they faced fierce
resistance from Chinese forces who had
adopted guerrilla warfare tactics,
sabotaging infrastructure and ambushing
patrols to harass and exhaust their
opponents. A campaign that some Japanese
generals thought would take only months
to complete had now turned into a war of
attrition. with the Japanese suffering
almost 600,000 casualties in China
before their attack on Pearl Harbor,
causing growing discontent amongst the
Japanese population, who saw a whole
generation of their young men shipped
overseas to fight in a conflict that
never seemed to end. Not only this, but
this war of expansion was quickly
becoming the biggest financial drain
upon the entire Japanese economy. By
1941, military expenditures accounted
for nearly 80% of government spending,
leaving no room for the production of
consumer goods, causing wages and the
standard of living to collapse across
the nation. Rather than reducing
reliance on western imports, as had been
the original objective of the military,
their territorial expansion, which
required vast sums of fuel for planes,
ships, and transports, would drastically
increase their reliance on imported oil,
rising from 67% in 1935, all the way up
to 90% in 1939. This would be Japan's
biggest vulnerability. If their war in
Asia was to continue, their supply of
oil could not be disrupted. Although the
situation was rapidly deteriorating for
the Japanese, events across the other
side of the globe would soon change the
situation altogether. Over in Europe,
the Second World War had broken out on
the continent with the British, French,
and Dutch fighting for survival against
Hitler's Germany. For Japan, this
presented a promising opportunity. With
these Western nations preoccupied in
Europe, the colonies they possessed in
Asia and the Pacific would now be ripe
for the taking. colonies that would not
only be easier to conquer than China,
but that could provide the vital raw
materials they needed and give the
Japanese civilian population a renewed
sense that military victory was around
the corner.
[Music]
Assuming power in 1933, President
Franklin D. Roosevelt, also known as
FDR, inherited a nation grappling with
the Great Depression and growing
international tensions. His popularity
was immense, riding a wave of optimism
and a mandate for change. With him
serving a historic four terms in office,
two more than any other president in
history. Thousands of Americans are here
to cheer the birth of a new era in
national affairs. A New Deal era which
is supposed to pull the country out of
its chaos. In foreign policy, Roosevelt
initially emphasized a good neighbor
policy with Latin America, seeking to
improve relations by reducing US
interventionism in the region. In Japan
2, he would take a similar approach,
mirroring the policy of his predecessor,
President Herbert Hoover, who had
refused to directly intervene when Japan
invaded Manuria in 1931.
However, as Japanese conquests across
the region continued, Roosevelt came to
believe that American intervention was
warranted, initially adopting a policy
of moral condemnation and refusing to
recognize the puppet state of Manchu
Quo. However, as time went on,
Roosevelt's intervention in the region
grew and grew with him beginning to send
money, arms, and other aid directly into
China to assist in their fight against
the Japanese.
With the Dutch and French having now
been conquered by Hitler's Germany,
Japan would look to take advantage of
their defenseless colonies in East Asia
with French Indo-China and the Dutch
East Indies being their first targets of
the region. From the Dutch, they would
demand greater access to their oil and
other raw material exports from the East
Indies. and from the British and French.
They would demand that the supply lines
from both Indochina and Burma be closed
off to stem the flow of aid to China.
These actions, however, would cause
growing concern in the United States
with President Roosevelt signing the
Export Control Act in July 1940,
restricting exports of aviation fuel,
steel, and scrap iron to Japan. This
embargo Roosevelt believed would be a
stern warning to the Japanese and would
be a way to curb their aggression
without resorting to direct military
intervention. However, far from
deterring the Japanese, these actions
drove them into the arms of Germany and
Italy with the three signing the
Tripartite Pact in September 1940. This
agreement stipulated that they would
assist each other with all political,
economic, and military means if one of
them was attacked by a nation not yet
involved in either the war in Europe or
China. It was effectively a direct
threat to the United States, warning
them that if they took military action
against the Japanese, they would be
declaring war on the combined forces of
Italy, Germany, and Japan. As the
Japanese foreign minister would state,
the pact would force the United States
to act more prudently in carrying out
her plans against Japan. While the
Japanese believed they had crafted a
plan that would lead to peace for the
British and Americans, by Japan signing
the pact, they were now viewed as no
better than their new allies, fascist
Italy and Nazi Germany. With these three
nations seen as little more than a group
of aggressor states that looked to
conquer the world,
Germany had conquered half of Europe.
Japan controlled a large part of China.
Between Japan's leaders and Adolf
Hitler, there was a perfect meeting of
minds and a complete understanding.
This alliance, however, would soon
present Japan with a promising
opportunity. Hitler's declaration of war
against the Soviet Union had placed
Stalin in a vulnerable position for the
Japanese. They now had a difficult
decision to make. Although they had
recently signed a non-aggression pact
with Stalin, this was an unprecedented
opportunity to take advantage of the
Soviets weakened state and to knock out
their historic rival once and for all,
guaranteeing Japanese superiority of
continental Asia. or they could continue
with their planned conquest to the south
where the vital supplies of oil were
located. The Japanese foreign minister
Yossuk Matsuoka was convinced that the
Germans would quickly defeat Russia and
that they should at once coordinate a
two-pronged attack with Hitler. As he
would state, "When Germany wipes out the
Soviet Union, we can't simply share in
the spoils of victory unless we've done
something." Hideki Tojo, the war
minister, was hesitant, however. If we
declare war on the Russians, would the
United States back them up and declare
war on us? After much debate and wanting
to avoid a two-pronged war, they decided
to forego the opportunity to attack the
Soviets and agreed that the resourcerich
colonies of Southeast Asia should be
their top priority. As Kenyo Sato, a
prominent military officer, stated, "We
gain nothing in the north. At least we
get oil and other resources in the
south." With the support of Germany and
Italy now secured and the pact with
Russia intact, Japan would be emboldened
to continue their conquest in Asia. With
French Indo-China becoming their next
target with France defeated and England
battling for its own existence,
Indochina with its rubber, tin,
tungsten, coal, and rice was to them a
treasure lying in the streets just
waiting to be picked up. And so in July
1941, they would deliver an ultimatum to
the Vishy French government declaring
that they would march into their colony
of Indochina with or without their
blessing. With no other option, the
French would concede, allowing Japanese
troops to enter the country on July
24th. It was a significant victory with
the Japanese ambassador in France
messaging Tokyo. The reason why the
French so readily accepted the Japanese
demands was that they saw how resolute
was our determination and how swift our
will. In short, they had no choice but
to yield. This time, however, Japan's
actions would provoke a more serious
response from the West. From America's
perspective, Japan's takeover of French
Indochina was a clear sign that their
dreams of empire were far greater than
just Manuria and China, and it was
something they would now have to stop.
As such, President Roosevelt, with the
backing of the British and Dutch, would
freeze all Japanese assets, halt all
trade, as well as enforce a complete
embargo of all oil exports to the
nation. As Japan imported almost 90% of
its oil, and had no natural reserves of
their own. This embargo threatened to
completely [__] both their economy
and ability to wage war. At current
rates of consumption, they would have at
best a year and a half supply of oil
left, giving them a definitive point at
which their empire would begin to
collapse. As the New York Times put it
on July 26th, it was the most drastic
blow short of actual war. Roosevelt knew
the risks and he had been warned by the
Navy War plans division that the embargo
would probably result in a fairly early
attack by Japan on Malaya and the Dutch
East Indies and possibly involved the
United States in an early war in the
Pacific. Despite this, for Roosevelt,
the potential to halt Japanese conquests
before they got out of hand was too
great an opportunity to pass. For the
Japanese, however, the American embargo
was viewed as an unacceptable and
hypocritical act of aggression. Japan
had gained the territory without firing
a single shot and had completed the
takeover within the realm of
international law. To them, their
occupation was nothing worse than what
the British or Americans had done with
their own colonies. With this embargo
signaling the final step in the
encirclement of their empire by what
they called the ABCD, the four hostile
powers of America, Britain, China, and
the Dutch. With their supply of oil now
completely cut off, Japanese leaders
were left with very few options. The
first would be to abandon their plans
for Southeast Asia completely and
retreat all the way back to Japan,
giving Russia and China control of the
region. Alternatively, they could work
out a compromise with the West in
exchange for the resumption of oil
imports. Or if that failed, the last
resort would be to attack the British
and Dutch colonies and take the
resources they needed by force. With the
first option thought of as completely
unacceptable by the entire Japanese
government, they would first pursue a
diplomatic solution with the West.
[Music]
With a diplomatic solution now to be
pursued, the task would be up to Japan's
new prime minister, Famaro Con, who had
taken power in July 1940. Born into one
of Japan's most influential aristocratic
families and a close personal friend of
Emperor Hirohito, Conier found support
across all aspects of Japanese society,
being described as a man of such wide
interests and objectivity that he could
listen with sympathy to those of all
political beliefs. In fact, he listened
with such sympathy that each in turn
thought the prince agreed with him.
However, Kanye's willingness to accept a
wide range of political views would not
only be his greatest strength, but also
his greatest flaw. With his ability to
hold seemingly opposite viewpoints on
the same topic, making his own political
beliefs difficult to discern, and
something others would look to take
advantage of, Kanye was a supporter of
Japan's imperial conquests, sharing the
view with the military that Japan should
be unquestionably the major uncontested
power of East Asia. He would also have a
growing interest in the ideological
tenets of fascism, particularly its
emphasis on national unity and strong
leadership, with him often willing to
concede to the ideas of strong-willed
militarists. Where he differed from the
military, however, was that he believed
war with the United States would almost
certainly prevent them from achieving
the empire they all looked to create. If
war was to break out, Kanye believed
that there was little chance of
overcoming America's industrial
potential. Not only this, but Kanye was
also a student of the prominent reformer
Saiji Kinmochi, the last surviving
statesman of the Maji generation. Saiji
warned that it was essential to
cooperate with Britain and America if
Japan was to thrive. With Kanyone
following in his mentors footsteps by
prioritizing a diplomatic solution to
the oil embargo crisis with the West. As
such, despite his many contradictions,
Kanye was viewed by most, including the
emperor himself, as the best chance
Japan had at avoiding war. If he was to
succeed, however, Kanye would have to
overcome a significant obstacle, the
military's uncontested power. The very
structure of the Japanese government had
ensured that none could oppose them,
which would make his negotiations with
the United States nearly impossible.
And the head of the government was the
emperor, a divine figure whose seal was
needed in order to officiate policy. To
the Japanese, the emperor was a living
god, the father to the nation, to whom
they would all pledge to serve to the
death. None in the country, except for
the most highranking generals and
government officials, had ever heard his
voice, with children taught that they
would go blind if they were ever to look
directly at his face.
Emperor Hirohito just like Kanye was a
student of the liberal reformer Prince
Sonji Kinmoji and as such was generally
against the idea of a full-scale war
with the United States. Having traveled
to the west himself, Hihito feared that
Japan would be unable to win against the
industrial power of America and would
therefore attempt to guide his
government away from the path of
conflict. However, despite his wishes to
avoid war, Hihito's ability to do so
would be extremely limited. With
tradition dictating that he was unable
to oppose a policy once it had been
decided upon by members of the
government and military, acting simply
as a figurehead, he would be presented
with these policies at imperial
conferences where he was expected to
remain silent and rubber stamp whatever
was put before him.
Not only this, but Japan would operate
under a unique dual government system
that divided power between civilian and
military authorities, both of which were
answerable only to the emperor himself.
Crucially, as the military had an
entirely separate chain of command, it
meant that neither the prime minister
nor any in the civilian government had
any direct control over them, allowing
the military to use their direct access
to the emperor in order to force through
advantageous policies without any
interference.
Not only this, but the Supreme Command
would have the power to veto any cabinet
decision that they believed infringed
upon military affairs, leaving the
government virtually powerless to oppose
them. With this power, they would be
able to pursue their ultimate goal of a
Japanese empire that dominated Asia and
the Pacific. Conier as head of the
civilian government would therefore have
the difficult task of not only reaching
a diplomatic compromise with the United
States but also keeping the military
happy so they did not interfere with
negotiations. In an attempt to keep the
military in check, Kanye would appoint a
new war minister, Hideki Tojo, a general
in the Imperial Army who was well known
and respected amongst the military ranks
for achieving a number of impressive
victories within China. A man of extreme
conviction, Tojo was known to never
waver on his ideals with him demanding
absolute discipline from his
subordinates. As such, although he
believed fully in Japan's divine right
of conquest, he had no tolerance for the
rebellious young officers whom he saw as
disgracing the nation. By appointing
Tojo, Kanye hoped he would be able to
keep these rogue members of the army in
check and finally help bring about some
muchneeded discipline and order. order
that would be crucial if negotiations
were to go well with the United
[Music]
States. To begin negotiations, Kanye
would first seek the military's
permission to open diplomatic channels
with the West. Despite harboring doubts
that they would lead to anything of
substance, the military would ultimately
agree, although they would put a hard
deadline on negotiations. October 10th,
1941, just two months away. If he had
not reached a settlement by this date,
they would resort to armed conflict.
With time now of their essence, Kanye
believed that a personal meeting with
Roosevelt was the only way he could
resolve the two countries many
differences and come to an agreement
before the army's deadline. "If the
president still does not see reason, I
shall of course be fully prepared to
break off the talks and return home,"
Kanye told Tojo and Navy Minister Okawa.
He believed negotiations were the best
path forward and that both nations would
have to make concessions if war was to
be averted. And so Kanye would send a
message on August 7th to Secretary of
State Cordell Hull requesting that he be
given an audience with Roosevelt to
discuss resolving the differences
between both countries.
[Music]
Hull, however, took a hardline approach
towards the Japanese and believed that
any sign of weakness on America's part
would only encourage their plans for
territorial expansion. A longtime
advocate for free trade and
international cooperation, Hull believed
that the promotion of these ideas would
promote economic interdependence and
discourage nations from resorting to
conflict. However, the rise of
aggressive regimes in Germany, Italy,
and Japan posed a significant challenge
to Hull's vision of a peaceful and
interconnected world with him being
increasingly distrustful of the
Japanese, who he saw as negotiating in
bad faith with their only goal to delay
Western interference in their conquests.
The spectre of a new descent into the
conditions of international anarchy,
which characterized the dark ages, looms
on the horizon today. Our own nation,
powerful as it is and determined as it
is to remain at peace, to preserve its
cherished institutions and to promote
the welfare of its citizens, is not
secure against that many. With both
Roosevelt and Hull coming to see a
conflict with Japan ever more likely,
the president came to hold two opposing
but pragmatic viewpoints. the wants to
settle negotiations diplomatically, but
also b time to strengthen their Pacific
fleet if negotiations fell through. As
Roosevelt would state to British Prime
Minister Winston Churchill in 1941, "If
negotiations with Japan failed, at the
very least, I think I can baby them
along for 3 months. It was a risky
policy, but if diplomacy failed, it
would hopefully buy them just enough
time to prepare for a conflict if one
was to occur. With these objectives in
mind, Hull upon receiving Conese's
proposal was extremely cautious,
believing that much like Hitler had done
to Chamberlain in Munich, it was simply
a ruse, a bid to buy time, and they had
no intention of keeping their word. As
such, Hull responded that it remained
with the Japanese government to decide
whether it could find means of shaping
its policies accordingly and then
endeavor to evolve some satisfactory
plan. Hull was essentially dismissing
Kanye's proposal outright and was
effectively stating that no official
meeting could take place until Japan
agreed to significant concessions for
the military agreeing to contact the
Americans at all was a significant
concession with Hull's dismissal causing
growing suspicion amongst Japanese
leaders. It appeared to them that rather
than a genuine desire for peace, the
Americans themselves were stalling for
time. time they could ill afford to lose
as each day 12,000 tons of irreplaceable
oil was being consumed. Although Hull's
response had stalled negotiations,
Roosevelt himself was open to the idea
of meeting with Kanye and stated that
the United States would be prepared to
reopen the unofficial preparatory
discussions which were broken off in
July and every effort will then be made
to select a time and place to exchange
views. However, the date he suggested
would be the middle of October, which
unknowingly would be the exact deadline
the military had given Kanye. Back in
Japan, many were beginning to have
serious reservations over a full-scale
war with America. Colonel Hideo Irakuro
would meet with several military and
political figures, urging that
negotiations must succeed, as America's
industrial potential would result in a
crushing Japanese defeat if a military
conflict was to occur. He contrasted the
alarming differences between American
and Japanese war potential. In steel, he
said the ratio was 20 to1, oil more than
100 to1, coal 10:1, planes 5:1, shipping
2:1, labor force 5:1. The overall
potential was 10:1. At such odds, Japan
could not possibly win despite Yamato
Damashi, the spirit of Japan. Although
not all would heed his words, many had
become sympathetic to Iwakuro's
arguments with the Supreme Command
capitulating and agreeing to allow major
concessions if it meant war was to be
averted. And so on August 28th, two
messages were sent to Roosevelt. The
first would be from Kanye yet again
requesting a meeting between himself and
the president with the second message
officially declaring that they would
withdraw all Japanese troops from French
Indo-China once the war with China had
been resolved promising to make no
further military advances into
neighboring countries and that they
would respect the Soviet Union's borders
as long as they did not attack Japanese
assets in Manchuko.
Not only this, but they would also agree
to abide by four basic principles
outlined by Hull as essential if any
negotiations were to take place. Number
one, respect for the territorial
integrity and the sovereignty of each
and all nations. Number two, support of
the principle of non-inference in the
internal affairs of other countries.
Number three, support of the principle
of equality, including equality of
commercial opportunity. Number four,
non-disturbance of the status quo in the
Pacific, except as the status quo may be
altered by peaceful means. This was a
drastic concession for the Japanese to
make. Not only were they willing to
negotiate on America's terms, but by
agreeing to the points the military
would have to halt their plans for the
expansion of the Japanese Empire. Upon
receiving the Japanese response,
Roosevelt was initially enthusiastic. At
long last, the two countries were
beginning to come to a compromise with
the president drawing up plans to spend
three muchneeded days with Conier.
However, not everyone was impressed.
American codereers had managed to crack
the Japanese diplomatic code, an
operation they called magic. This
breakthrough granted US officials,
including Secretary of State Hull,
unprecedented access to the confidential
communications of high-ranking Japanese
officials, often knowing of their
intentions, strategies, and negotiating
positions before official meetings even
took place. As such, Hull and others
were usually dismissive of any direct
correspondence or outreaches by the
Japanese government, often coming to
conclusions based on these magic reports
alone. accompanying the latest Japanese
proposals were new magic intercepts,
indicating that a significant new
military buildup was taking place in
Southeast Asia. For Hull, this was a
clear sign of Japanese deception. How
could Kanye's outreach be genuine with
the promise to withdraw troops from
Indochina if their military was
preparing for war? Sharing his concerns
with Roosevelt, the president's earlier
optimism completely vanished with him
and Hull deciding that a meeting with
the Japanese would now be impossible
unless an even more explicit guarantee
was given that the American demands
would be
met. However, America's ambassador in
Tokyo, Joseph C. Gru, would come to a
completely different opinion. Grrew was
considered a legend in the State
Department, having served as a diplomat
for nearly 40 years and in 14 different
posts with St. Petersburg and Berlin
being amongst them. Having great
affection for Japan as well as his wife,
both speaking Japanese and being a
descendant of Matthew Perry, the US
Commodore who had commanded the black
ships nearly a century ago, Grrew was
considered the best choice for
ambassador to Japan when conflict broke
out in Manuria in
1931. Having been stationed there for
now nearly a decade, Grrew had come to
develop a deep understanding of both the
complexities of the Japanese system as
well as the thoughts and desires of
those in key leadership positions. The
Japanese aren't easy to
know. I've lived among them for 10
years. You cannot measure Japanese sense
of logic by any western yard stick. With
the Americans having yet again dismissed
Japan's attempts to have a face-to-face
meeting, army leaders began to grow
increasingly agitated with even the
emperor himself now urging for a
diplomatic solution to be the nation's
top priority. As a result, Kanye would
meet with Gru in person and attempt to
resolve their differences. "What about
Hull's four principles?" Grrew would ask
the prime minister. "They were generally
acceptable," Kanye replied. "However,
when it comes to applying them
practically, various problems will
arise, and to solve them, I must have a
meeting with the president." Although
Kanye was unable to reveal it to Grun,
the deadline the military had set him to
complete negotiations was only a month
away and he understood that at this
point using regular diplomatic channels
would simply be far too slow and so
urged again that a face-to-face meeting
was vital if they were to settle their
differences. A year from now I am not
sure that anything can be done to solve
our differences, Kanye stated, but I can
do now. I promise that some agreement
can be reached if I can only see him. on
offer him a proposal which he can't
afford to reject. Grrew believed Con's
plea to meet with the president was
sincere and the fact that the prime
minister had agreed to abide by Hull's
four principles gave Grrew the sense
that Kanye was genuine in his attempts
to bring hostilities to an end via
diplomatic means. As a result, Grrew
told Conier that he would go back to the
embassy immediately and send his message
to Washington, something he touted as
the most important cable of his
diplomatic career.
The ambassador stresses the importance
of understanding Japanese psychology
fundamentally unlike that of any western
nation. Japanese reactions to any
particular set of circumstances cannot
be measured, nor can Japanese actions be
predicted by any western measuring rod.
Should the United States expect or await
agreement by the Japanese government in
the present preliminary conversations to
clear-cut commitments which will satisfy
the United States government both as to
principle and as to concrete detail?
Almost certainly the conversations will
drag along indefinitely and
unproductively until the Kanye cabinet
and its supporting elements desiring
reproachment with the United States will
come to the conclusion that the outlook
for an agreement is hopeless and that
the United States government is only
plain for time. This will result in the
Kier's government being discredited and
in a revulsion of anti-American feeling
and this may and probably will lead to
unbridled acts.
[Music]
Despite Gru's message, however, Hull and
the American leadership had already
largely made up their minds, dismissing
his cable as the concerns of an
ambassador who had grown too close to
Japan. Therefore, rather than following
Gru's advice, Hull would respond to
Conier and rather than clarifying or
softening his terms, would instead ask
for a concession that was almost certain
to guarantee war. All Japanese troops,
he demanded, must be completely
withdrawn from China without delay if a
meeting between Kanye and Roosevelt was
to be arranged. Having received the
response, Kanye would gather the top
officials from across the nation to
discuss the issue at his villa in Okubo.
But the army, to little surprise, were
infuriated by Hull's demands. For them,
the American position was now clear. To
demand such concessions without a
meeting even taking place meant only one
thing. It appeared as though they were
only trying to buy time. With every
sincere Japanese outreach to meet a
settlement, either being met with
mockery or complete dismissal,
attempting to move negotiations forward,
Foreign Minister Tiro Toya would speak
first. I think the thorniest issue today
is the presence of troops in China. And
if the army won't concede a thing to the
United States, then there's no point in
continuing the talks. But if the army
can see its way clear to making some
slight compromise, it may not be
impossible. Furious, War Minister Tojo
would respond immediately. The
stationing of troops is a matter of life
and death to the army. No concessions in
that direction. Japan had already agreed
in principle to the withdrawal of all
troops from China. He continued, "That
in itself was a tremendous concession.
Now it was obvious that America was
demanding that Japan withdraw all troops
at once. This was impossible. A million
Japanese were still locked in battle in
China. Japan could not withdraw
completely until order was restored in
China. The interior was a hotbed of
communists and bandits and only the
presence of Japanese troops in certain
areas could guarantee law and order and
the successful economic growth of that
whole part of the continent. Total
withdrawal before the aims of war had
been accomplished would not be in
keeping with the dignity of the army and
the entire general staff as well as the
troops abroad agreed with
him. Why not give in to America in form?
and Kanye replied. That is agree in
principle to withdraw all troops, yet
make an arrangement with China to retain
some troops in unstable areas. That
would not be tenable, said Tojo. If they
made the pledge to withdraw all troops
from the region, they would have to
honor their word. And not only this, but
if they gave in to American demands,
China would see Japan as weak, and soon
uprisings could spring up, not only in
China, but Korea as well. Despite being
the only man present arguing for war,
Tojo refused to back down. I don't think
there is any possible way to settle the
problem by diplomacy at this stage, he
would state. Conier, however, held the
complete opposite opinion, believing
that war with the US was futile and that
a meeting with Roosevelt was still
Japan's best option. I'm not confident
of victory in war, he stated. I think
there is no way to overcome the present
difficulties except by diplomatic
negotiations. Tojo's forceful remarks
would continue throughout the afternoon
until finally the men assembled would
reach a decision. Con would have until
October 15th a 5-day extension to finish
negotiations with the United States, but
the army under no circumstances would
concede anything on the removal of their
troops from China. However, while Kanye
had initially approved of the
compromise, he would come to regret it
almost immediately. The removal of
troops from China appeared to be the
only thing the Americans were interested
in, and without this vital bargaining
chip, he was unlikely to be able to come
to any sort of agreement with Roosevelt.
Phoning Tojo on October 14th, one day
before the deadline was due, he would
plead with the war minister to
reconsider. I can go along with you
except for your stand on our troops in
China, he would state. But Tojo's reply
was swift and uncompromising. If once we
give in, the United States will assume a
high-handed attitude and keep on acting
that way. Your solution is really not a
solution. War will crop up again in a
few years. I respect you, Mr. Prime
Minister, but your view is too
pessimistic. You know our weak points
too well. America has her weaknesses,
too. That same day, the cabinet
assembled yet again to discuss the issue
of China. The army will continue its
preparation, said Tojo. I don't mean
this will necessarily interfere with the
negotiations, but I will not consider
another day's delay. However, foreign
minister Toyota would state that it was
paramount that they give the US a clear
and straightforward response. America is
becoming more and more suspicious of our
attitude. So, we can't satisfy them
unless we give them facts. They cannot
understand Japan's way of carrying on
peace talks while preparing for war.
Tojo, however, refused to give any
ground. This time shouting, "I make no
concessions regarding withdrawal. It
means defeat of Japan by the United
States, a stain on the history of the
Japanese Empire. The way of diplomacy
isn't always a matter of concession.
Sometimes it is oppression. If we
concede, Manuria and Korea will be
lost." Tojo's outburst had stunned the
cabinet into silence. Shocked that the
war minister had expressed such a
forceful opinion. It left Conier with
very few options. The war minister's
refusal to concede on the matter of
China meant that negotiations with the
US were now impossible. Continuing as
prime minister would force Kanye down
the path of war and as such he saw no
option but to resign. Kier's decision
was a deadly blow for those in Japan who
still wanted peace. Even generals in the
army were alarmed at the prince's
resignation. General Muto, although
believing Kanye to be a coward, thought
he was the only man capable of
maintaining national unity with his
absence guaranteeing division and
infighting. If he resigns, the general
stated, "Japan cannot fight a war."
However, to the dismay of many in the
government, Kanye's resignation would
come sooner than expected. On October
16th, he would inform Kohici Kido, the
emperor's chief adviser, of his
resignation. With the choice of his
successor now on everybody's mind, both
the new prime minister and the cabinet
would be the most consequential and
important one to date, with the
responsibility to assemble a government
capable of bringing about peace now
falling on Keo shoulders.
[Music]
Known as a calculating and pragmatic
man, Keido, just like the emperor,
supported diplomacy and international
cooperation. Believing that a war with
the West would spell disaster for Japan.
With tradition dictating that the
emperor was unable to become directly
involved in politics, Keido would act as
his representative, expressing
Hirohito's wishes during imperial
conferences and helping to guide the
government from behind the scenes.
Wishing to avoid war, but also
recognizing the need to keep the
military under control, Keo was left
with few options when appointing the new
prime minister. To handle this delicate
situation, Keido believed it would have
to be somebody already familiar with the
negotiations and also someone respected
enough for both the government and army
to follow their wishes. This left Kido
with only two options, Navy Minister
Admiral Koshiro Oikua and War Minister
Hideki Tojo. Oawa was a promising
candidate, having already shown signs of
favoring a diplomatic solution to the
crisis. Despite this, however, Keo
didn't believe that Oawa commanded the
respect of the fanatical young officers
who constantly threatened to take
military action against the government.
Despite Tojo being the main opponent to
peace up until this point, only he, Kido
believed, would control these dangerous
military elements and prevent them from
rebelling if peace was ultimately
favored over war. He also thought that
Tojo was a man of honor with few
political ambitions and a deep
admiration for hierarchy. Something that
could be exploited if he were to get the
emperor to intervene and direct the
prime minister toward a path of peace.
It was a dangerous gamble, but one Keo
was willing to take. And so, with the
blessing of the Juin, a council of
Japan's seven former prime ministers,
Tojo would be appointed as prime
minister on October 16th. Unlike
previous prime ministers, however, Tojo
would also retain the role of war
minister, combining the two roles into
one. Apart from the emperor, he was now
the most powerful man in the nation,
presiding over both the government and
military with the power of both branches
having been consolidated into his hands.
And the one man who could satisfy
Japan's powerful war party, General
Hidei Tojo, became prime minister. into
office with him. In October
1941, General Tojo brought faithful
admirals and generals who had served the
war
party. The removal of Premier Kenoi in
favor of Tojo meant that the great
decision had been made. Japan was
setting out
irrevocably upon its path of conquest in
the Pacific.
The Americans, by seeking to delay
negotiations for as long as possible,
had inadvertently removed Prince Con,
the man best suited to achieving peace.
In his place was now Hideki Tojo, not
only a man that lacked the diplomatic
expertise of his predecessor, but had
consolidated the power of the war
minister and prime minister into one
position. The American strategy had
seemingly backfired with Gru's warnings
having come to fruition. A growing
conflict in Asia was now more likely
than ever. However, there remained one
last chance for
peace. Kedo, still intent on reaching a
diplomatic solution, would now implement
a plan that he had formulated when he
had suggested Tojo for the position.
Knowing that Tojo was a devout follower
of the imperial system and would obey an
order from the emperor no matter the
cost, Keido would now look to use this
to his advantage, taking an
unprecedented action that had never been
seen before. The emperor, a divine
figure who tradition dictated remained
above politics, was now to intervene
directly and order that his government
was to prioritize diplomatic efforts.
Despite all odds favoring war, there
were still those in Japan who favored a
peaceful resolution. Having conferred
with Hirohito, Keido would then speak to
Tojo after his appointment to prime
minister, where he would relay a direct
message from the emperor. It is his
majesty's wish, Kido stated, that Tojo
go back to blank paper, ignore the
previous deadline that had been set, and
make every effort to renew negotiations
with America in the pursuit of peace. It
was an unprecedented move. Never in
Japanese history had the emperor
overruled a decision of an imperial
conference and intervened so forcefully
in the affairs of government. Tojo
having a deep admiration and respect for
the emperor bowed to his wishes and
stated he would pursue a diplomatic
solution. It appeared for now that Keo's
plan had
worked. Having been directed to find a
diplomatic solution to the crisis, Tojo
would now appoint a new foreign minister
to direct negotiations. The man he chose
would be Shiganori Togo, an experienced
politician who had an excellent
understanding of Western culture, having
even caused a scandal in Japan by
marrying a German woman. Pragmatic to
the core, Togo was often blunt and
direct to the point, but always wished
to negotiate in good faith with him soon
drafting two proposals that he thought
the United States and Japan could agree
upon. Proposal A stipulated that Japan
would bring the war with China to an end
and they would remove all troops from
the country by 1966. If proposal A was
rejected, a fallback position, proposal
B would then be offered, which would
give even more concessions and aimed to
assure Halt that Japan was no longer
interested in pursuing military
expansion in Southeast Asia. This
proposal stated that there would be no
further expansion to the South or
Pacific and agreed to an immediate
withdrawal of troops from southern
Indochina with their remaining forces
stationed there to be removed once the
war with China had come to an end. In
return for these significant
concessions, the United States were to
unfreeze Japanese assets and lift the
oil embargo that was strangling the
Japanese economy and military. However,
when Togo presented his proposals during
the Imperial Conference of November 1st,
he would come across stubborn
resistance. The army's highest ranking
officer, General Hajime Sugyama, would
be the first to voice his objections.
Stationing troops in French Indo-China
keeps China under control and also
enables us to get raw materials in the
south on a 50/50 basis. Moreover, it
places us in a stronger position
strategically towards the United States
as well as in setting the China
incident. Coming to an agreement with
the United States doesn't mean they will
give us materials. We are against
proposal B. The only alternative Sugama
proposed was to insist that Hull
unfreeze their assets without offering
any concessions at all. A suggestion so
ridiculous that Togo began to lose his
temper. You're putting me in a difficult
position if you tell me to do something
that can't be done. Things got so heated
that a brief recess was called with
Prime Minister Tojo speaking to the
military men privately to remind them of
their duty to their emperor. The emperor
had asked for blank paper. He stated,
"We must follow his wishes and bring
about a diplomatic solution if
possible." It was only now with the
emperor's wishes being evoked that the
army would concede with Sugiama
reluctantly giving his approval for
proposals A and B. For the military, it
was a huge concession, one that
threatened to cause discontent with the
rebellious young officers and breed
resentment throughout their ranks.
However, the deal was done, but it had
come at the cost of one stipulation. A
new and final deadline had been set,
December 1st. If Togo couldn't reach an
agreement by this date, then war with
the United States would
commence. For foreign minister Togo, the
delicate task of delivering his
proposals to the Americans would now be
left in the hands of the Japanese
ambassador in Washington, Kichi Saburo
Namora. Being good-natured and
straightforward, Namora had been a
career naval officer, rising to the rank
of admiral before becoming the Japanese
ambassador to the United States in 1940.
It was his belief that war with America
would be disastrous for Japan, and he
would do everything in his power to make
sure such an outcome did not occur.
Despite his good intentions, however,
Namora was prone to diplomatic blunders
and had failed to make any significant
progress while negotiating with Hull. As
such, Togo would now send a special
envoy to assist him, Saburro Kusu.
Kurusu was considered a confident and
reliable diplomat, having signed the
tripartite pact on Japan's behalf, while
also having a good understanding of
Western culture and customs, with his
own wife being an American of British
descent. sharing Namora's conviction
that war with the United States should
be avoided at all costs. If anybody from
Japan was to secure peace, it would be
these two who could do it.
On November 14th, Mr. Kurissu arrived in
San Francisco. We all know how difficult
my mission is, but I'll do all I can to
make it a successful one for the sake of
two countries, the bad and the United
States.
Despite this, however, their path to a
negotiated peace would be more difficult
than they had imagined. Alongside
Roosevelt and Hull, they would also have
to deal with Dr. Stanley Hornbeck,
Hull's chief adviser on the Far East.
Having grown up in China, Hornbeck
retained a deep distrust of the
Japanese, believing they were a
predatory power run by arrogant
militarists. Convinced that it was a
moral duty of a larger power like the
United States to curb Japanese
aggression, it was a strong advocate of
economic sanctions, believing their use
was necessary, even if it resulted in
war. Another American overseeing
negotiations would be Secretary of War
Henry Stimson. Having previously served
as Secretary of State under President
Hoover, Stimpson had opposed Japanese
expansionism since their invasion of
Manuria, a policy known as the Stimson
Doctrine. Ever since, he had worked to
build up America's forces in the Pacific
and was yet another advocate of the
economic sanctions and oil embargo that
Roosevelt had placed on
Japan. Although these men, along with
many others in the American camp,
remained deeply hostile and suspicious
of any Japanese concessions, there would
still be one man who passionately tried
to warn them of the significance of
Togo's proposals they were about to
receive. Being stationed in Japan,
Ambassador Gru had witnessed the growing
tensions amongst the Japanese leadership
firsthand and saw that they were growing
increasingly frustrated with America's
dismissive attitude at their attempts to
negotiate. As he noted in his diary in
early November, Japan is obviously
preparing a program of war to be carried
out if her alternative program of peace
should fail. Result to the former may
come with dramatic and dangerous
suddeness. Realizing that war was closer
than ever, he would send a cable to
Washington trying to convey the severity
of the situation. If these efforts fail,
the ambassador foresees a probable swing
of the pendulum in Japan once more back
to the former Japanese position or even
farther. This would lead to what he has
described as an allout do or die
attempt, actually risking national Harry
Kiri to make Japan impervious to
economic embargos abroad rather than to
yield to foreign pressure.
Grrew would not be alone in his dire
assessment of the situation with
Ottolicious providing American readers
with the events from the Japanese
perspective and just how close to war
they really were. As he wrote in the New
York Times, "The Japanese listen to
alarming statements by the highest
government officials about the greatest
crisis Japan has ever faced in her
2,600year history. They are called to
mass meetings to hear denunciations of
the enemy and they read a steady clamor
in the press. They see shelters and
water reservoirs being built everywhere
in preparation for air raids. They are
being drilled in air raid defense,
especially in fighting fires, the
biggest dread of Japanese cities.
Finally, they see taxes and prices
rising. They know that all these things
are not done for fun and that war, real
war, which only a short while ago seemed
so far away, is rapidly stretching out
its fiery arms toward Nippon, land of
the gods. The people do not want war,
but neither do they want to give up the
fruits of the war they have been
fighting, which has cost them such a lot
of blood and treasure. They have been
told that this war is a war of
self-defense to obtain elbow room for
the Japanese people crowded into a few
small islands with few natural resources
and to liberate 1,000 million of
oriental peoples from exploitation by
the white race. However, neither
articles like this nor Gru's firsthand
assessment of the situation would be
taken seriously. Stanley Hornbeck,
Hull's chief adviser, would dismiss
Gru's message entirely, believing him to
be gullible, with his love for Japan
blinding him to their true intentions.
Unfortunately for Roosevelt, his
advisers thought they knew better than
the man stationed on the ground in
Japan.
Not only this, but Hornbeck and other
members of the American leadership had
been receiving an increasing number of
messages from their magic intercepts of
Japan's diplomatic messages, indicating
that they were still preparing for war
despite the claims that they wanted
peace. As such, American diplomats were
becoming increasingly harsh in their
responses to the Japanese, believing
that the magic intercepts they were
presented with contained all the
information they needed to know.
However, not only did these intercepts
not provide the full context of the
conversations between Japanese high
command, but they were also badly
translated, often changing their entire
meaning. In this example, as highlighted
by historian John Toland, foreign
minister Togo would send a confidential
message to Ambassador Namora outlining
proposals A and B and stressing the
importance of negotiations. Strenuous
efforts are being made day and night to
adjust Japanese American relations which
are on the verge of rupture. When this
message was intercepted and delivered to
Hull, however, the translation would
have a much more negative tone. Well,
the relations between Japan and the
United States have reached the edge and
our people are losing confidence in the
possibility of ever adjusting them. This
would continue again and again with Hull
and others in the State Department
reading translations with a far
different meaning than had been
intended. For some historians, this
point would become a contentious issue
with some attributing it purely to
inexperienced and poorly trained
translators, while others mainly in
Japan believe that these and many other
diplomatic messages were purposefully
mistransated.
[Music]
When Ambassador Namura met with Hull on
November 7th to present him with
proposal A, Hull, having read through
the magic intercept of the same text
over the past several days, would
dismiss it entirely. Skimming through
the pages with haste, having already
made up his mind that the proposal
offered very few concessions. Although
Hull did little to hide his animosity
towards the Japanese, he was still
careful not to break off negotiations
entirely, the American chiefs of staff,
General Marshall and Admiral Stark, were
both insistent on delaying war with
Japan for as long as possible. As they
would warn President Roosevelt, a war
with Japan could seriously hinder the
Allied struggle against Germany and that
no ultimatum should be given to the
Japanese for at least 4 months in order
to build up American forces in the
Pacific. A week after Hull had been
given proposal A, Special Envoy Kurusu
would finally arrive in Washington to
assist Namura with the negotiations,
with the pair now presenting Hull with
proposal B, which contains the most
significant concessions to date. Upon
seeing Kusu, however, Hull was
immediately distrustful. The envoy he
knew had signed the Tripartite pact, a
document he viewed as both antagonistic
and hostile. And beyond that, he simply
disliked Kusu, later writing in his
memoirs. Neither his appearance nor his
attitude commanded confidence or
respect. I felt from the start that he
was deceitful. His only recommendation,
in my eyes, was that he spoke excellent
English, having married his American
secretary. He was sure that Kusu's only
objective was to lull us with talk until
the moment Japan got ready to strike.
And so when Hull was presented with
proposal B, he was not only dismissive,
but even began to lose his temper,
writing in his memoirs that their
proposals were of so preposterous a
character that no American official
could ever have dreamed of accepting
them. To Namura and Kusu, the
concessions outlined in proposal B had
come at great difficulty, with the
emperor himself having intervened to
make sure they had come to pass. The
military too had given far more grounds
than their honor allowed, even risking a
coup from the young officers by pledging
to remove troops from southern
Indochina. For Hull, however, he viewed
the concessions as simply another
attempt of Japanese duplicity. It was
not really a question of proposal B
itself, but of State Department refusal
to accept it at face value. What the
Japanese army considered a major
concession and had accepted only after
bitter argument withdrawal of troops
from southern Indochina to the north was
scorned. It was a meaningless offer
since the Japanese could easily return
the same troops to southern Indochina
within a day or two. Despite having no
intentions of ever accepting the terms,
Hull would decide to abide by the wishes
of the American chiefs of staff to
string along the Japanese for as long as
possible, telling the two diplomats that
he would give the proposal, quote,
sympathetic study. This would, in Hull's
words, avoid giving the Japanese any
pretext to walk out of the
conversations. Despite Hull's pessimism,
Roosevelt, however, would view proposal
B in a more favorable light, believing
it offered a glimpse of hope for
negotiations. Agreeing with the chiefs
of staff that war should be avoided for
as long as possible, he would draft a
modus Vendi, a temporary agreement, and
send it to Hull, outlining a potential
response that could reopen negotiations.
For the next 6 months, it would state
the US would resume a limited amount of
oil and rice trade to Japan. In
exchange, the Japanese would refrain
from sending any further troops into
Indo-China, the Manurion border, or the
European colonies to the south. The
Japanese would also have to pledge that
they would not go to war under the
Tripartite Pact if the United States
decided to declare war against Germany.
And finally, the United States would act
as a mediator between China and Japan to
help bring the war to an end. Upon
receiving Roosevelt's note, Hull,
despite his reservations, would make
plans to move ahead with negotiations,
taking the modus Vendi to the Allied
powers for their approval. Upon doing
so, however, he would come up against
great opposition from the Chinese with
their leader, Chang Kaishek, stating
that this was an indication that the US
was inclined to appease Japan at the
expense of China. Churchill too believed
there were not enough guarantees for
China, as he would cable to Roosevelt.
Of course, it is for you to handle this
business, and we certainly do not want
an additional war. There is only one
point that disqus us. What about
Changaiek? Is he not having a very thin
diet? Our anxiety is about China. If
they collapse, our joint dangers would
enormously increase. The objections of
the Chinese and British would be enough
to convince Hull that a tougher stance
on Japan was needed. Not only this, but
a new magic intercept would soon be
delivered to him, detailing a
conversation between Tokyo and Namora.
November 26, Washington. A decoded
message from Tokyo is prepared for the
State
Department. Urgent to both you
ambassadors. There must be an agreement
by November 29th. This time we mean it.
The deadline absolutely cannot be
changed. After that, things are
automatically going to happen. For Hull
and Under Secretary Sumar Wells, the
crisis deepens, but there will be no
appeasement.
Sharing the message with Roosevelt and
Stimson, all three men would take it as
confirmation that war was inevitable.
With Stimson writing in his diary,
"Roosevelt brought up the event that we
were likely to be attacked perhaps next
Monday, December 1st, for the Japanese
are notorious for making an attack
without warning, and the question was
what we should do." The question was how
we should maneuver them into the
position of firing the first shot
without allowing too much danger to
ourselves. It was a difficult
proposition. The following day, with his
allies not receptive to the proposals
and believing a Japanese attack was
imminent, Hull would abandon Roosevelt's
modus Vendi altogether, instead drafting
a far harsher response. But notably, he
would do this without consulting General
Marshall or Admiral Stark, who still
desired for negotiations to be
prolonged, known as the 10point demand.
He would present it to Ambassador Kurusu
and Namora on November 26th with it
demanding that Japan withdraw all
military, naval, air, and police forces
from China and Indo-China, support no
other government or regime in China
except for Chiang Kai-sheks and in
exchange the United States would
unfreeze all Japanese assets. Even with
these concessions being demanded of the
Japanese, Hull had still failed to
address the biggest issue they faced,
the oil
embargo. Upon reading Hull's note, the
Japanese ambassadors were shocked. The
note was effectively a declaration of
war. There was no chance those in Tokyo,
even those who sought peace, would ever
agree to an immediate withdrawal of all
troops from China. A move that would
surely lead to the collapse of
everything the Japanese had worked so
hard to gain over the past decade.
Knowing what the response would be back
home, Kusu would attempt to reason with
her. Negotiations would be impossible,
he would state, if it expected Japan to
take off its hat to Chiang Kai-shek and
apologize to him. Surely some other
compromise could be reached. It is as
far as we can go, Hull would reply.
There was nothing more to be done, the
note was sent back to
Tokyo. With the negotiations with Japan
seemingly having come to an end, an
urgent alert was sent to the commanders
in the Far East, including General
Douglas MacArthur, who was stationed in
the Philippines, which read the
following. Negotiations with the
Japanese appear to be terminated to all
practical purposes with only the barest
possibilities that the Japanese
government might come back and offer to
continue. Japanese future action
unpredictable but hostile action
possible at any moment. If hostilities
cannot repeat cannot be avoided, the
United States desires that Japan commit
the first overt act. This policy should
not, repeat not, be construed as
restricting you to a course of action
that might jeopardize your defense. The
road to war had been set, and a conflict
in the Pacific was soon to come to
fruition.
Receiving Hull's 10-point demand the
next day on November 27th, the response
would be read aloud by Prime Minister
Tojo in a meeting of Japan's top
government and military officials. As
Tojo finished reading the note, the room
fell silent in disbelief. This is an
ultimatum, one man would shout, with
another, Admiral Sheimeda, declaring
Hull's note to be a jarring blow, as
well as unyielding and unbending in its
failure to acknowledge any of the
concessions that had taken such great
effort to achieve. The most egregious
point would be Hull's demand for an
immediate withdrawal from China.
Although Hull had intended this point
not to include Manuria, the wording of
his response left this incredibly
ambiguous with the Japanese assuming he
was demanding they abandoned the
territory they had won all the way back
in 1932. The loss of Manuria would spell
economic disaster for Japan, considering
the amount of time and resources they
had poured into the region, let alone
the blood they had spilled to claim it.
From the Japanese perspective, Hull's
note was clearly designed to be
impossible to accept. Yet another
stalling tactic to entice Japan into
striking the first blow. America had
made up her mind and was ready to go to
war. The negotiations they had earnestly
thought would bring about peace had been
in vain. From the Japanese perspective,
America had simply been stalling for
time. On December 1st, 1941, with the
deadline having finally been reached,
Emperor Hirohito would comply with the
wishes of his military and government
and conceded to declaring war on the
United States. Following in Japan's
historic tradition of surprise attacks,
a plan months in the making would now be
put underway to begin the war by
striking at the American naval base at
Pearl Harbor.
[Music]
With Japan now on the path to war, their
hopes of success would lie on the
shoulders of Admiral Isaraku Yamamoto, a
highly gifted naval officer and
commanderin-chief of the Japanese
combined fleet. However, when Yamamoto
had assumed his position as head of the
Japanese naval forces, he had found the
existing plan for war against the United
States to be completely inadequate.
Japan's admirals had been expecting the
Americans to launch an all-out attack on
their fleet close to the home islands
with a decisive battle then culminating
in Japanese waters where their navy
reigned supreme. Much like the decisive
battles of the past, such as when the
legendary Admiral Togo had wiped out the
Russian fleet at the Battle of Tushima,
it would be this coming battle just off
the coast of Japan that would bring
about the victory they had hoped for.
However, this strategy Yamamoto believed
was reactive and relied too heavily on
the United States to make the first
move. Instead, upon taking command of
the Japanese combined fleet, he would
look for a different strategy, drawing
upon his knowledge of modern naval
warfare. Having spent many years in
America, studying at Harvard University
and acting as a naval diplomat in
Washington, Yamamoto was well aware of
the vast industrial potential the United
States possessed, which would
undoubtedly overwhelm Japan if a
prolonged conflict was to break out. As
such, he was an open critic of war with
the United States. A stance that put him
in danger of assassination by fanatical
army ultraists, with him warning Prime
Minister Conier in 1941. In the first 6
to 12 months of a war with the United
States and Great Britain, I will run
wild and win victory upon victory. But
then, if the war continues after that, I
have no expectation of success. When war
seemed all but inevitable, however,
Yamamoto would reluctantly take on
responsibility for planning the attack.
A natural risk-taker, he was known as an
expert gambler, being proficient in
games of luck and strategy such as
poker, bridge, shogi, and go. As such,
he was willing to risk everything in one
daring attack that was aimed at wiping
out the American fleet before the
conflict even began. Taking inspiration
from his hero, the legendary Admiral
Togo, whom Yamamoto had served under 35
years ago during the Russo-Japanese War,
he would now look to launch a surprise
attack of his own, just like Togo had
done all those years ago that had
successfully crippled the Russian fleet.
This time, however, it would not be the
Russians that were his targets, but the
American naval base at Pearl Harbor.
Yamamoto also believed that it was vital
to destroy America's aircraft carriers
in the attack, as he saw them as being
the true heart of a modern navy as
opposed to battleships, as many of his
contemporaries still believed. Removing
America's aircraft carriers now would
give Japan the best chance it had to
secure domination over the Pacific.
Along with the importance of taking out
the American carriers, attacking Pearl
Harbor would also open up the way for
Japanese conquests to the south. With
negotiations with the US having failed,
they were now desperate to acquire a new
source of oil. With the Dutch East
Indies and their plentiful oil fields
now ripe for the taking. However, the
flow of these resources back to Japan
could still be disrupted by American
forces in the Philippines with the
neutralization of this American outpost
a necessity if their plan was to be
successful. The Philippines, however,
would prove difficult to take. Not only
was it an important American base under
the command of renowned General Douglas
MacArthur, but if war was to break out,
it could be supplied and reinforced with
troops and ships from Pearl Harbor.
Taking out Pearl Harbor, therefore,
would be a top priority, as it would
leave the Philippines isolated and
exposed for the taking. The attack
Yamamoto hoped would therefore give
Japan time, around 6 months, to seize
the Dutch East Indies and secure control
of Southeast Asia and the Western
Pacific without American interference.
During this time, Japan could also begin
construction of new battleships and
aircraft carriers, increasing its
presence and naval might in the region.
With the Pacific securely under Japanese
control and the American fleet having
been completely wiped out, they would
now be able to establish a defensive
perimeter, something they referred to as
the absolute national defense zone, a
vertical line that stretched from
western New Guinea to the Cural Islands
north of mainland Japan. The territory
within this zone would be referred to as
the Greater East Asia co-rossperity
sphere and would ensure that the
Japanese could transport the vital
resources of oil, tin, and rubber from
their conquests back to the homeland
without interference from the Western
powers. If all went according to plan
and with their power now uncontested
across the region, Yamamoto believed
that the United States would be forced
to accept Japanese dominance in East
Asia. With a prolonged conflict between
the two nations becoming an unthinkable
idea, Japan was to be so strong and well
positioned that the Americans would be
foolish even to consider war.
Pearl Harbor itself was stationed in
Hawaii, an American territory in the
Pacific that was a vital part of US
defense in the region due to its central
location and proximity to Asia, acting
as a potential buffer against Japanese
expansionism.
Its deep water harbor, extensive repair
facilities, and ample supplies made it
an ideal location for the American Navy
to station its fleet, with the base also
serving as a vital hub for
communications and intelligence
gathering. As such, the base at Pearl
Harbor was home to a majority of the
USPacific fleet, including three
carriers, eight battleships, eight
cruisers, and 30 destroyers, with it
acting as a forward operating base for
projecting American power into the
region. Pearl Harbor itself was
stationed on the central island of Aahu,
located just west of the capital city of
Honolulu. Although home to around 40,000
military personnel, peaceime liberties
had been granted, with the men stationed
there making use of the many luxuries
the tropical island provided. This
relaxed atmosphere, however, would be
something the Japanese look to exploit
with Admiral Yamamoto sending a spy,
Takio Yoshiwa, on a reconnaissance
mission to infiltrate the island and
gather as much vital information as
possible, disguising himself as a
tourist, wearing sunglasses and a bright
Hawaiian shirt. Yoshiwa would drive
around the island twice a week and visit
Pearl Harbor every day, memorizing the
length of the main runways, as well as
the numbers of planes, pilots, hangers,
and soldiers, delivering all of this
information back to Tokyo. The security
on the island was so lax, in fact, that
Yoshiwa was able to infiltrate the
American naval base several times, even
managing to scuba dive underneath the
harbor to check the integrity of the
torpedo nets that protected the ship
stationed there. Once armed with a
lunchbox, he followed a group of
laborers and spent the day wandering
around without being questioned. He
tapped a big oil tank to see how much
was inside and discovered that full
tanks usually leaked and could easily be
detected from outside the fence. With
the essential information Yoshiawa
provided now in Yamamoto's hands, he was
able to finalize his plans for the
attack. By April, Yamamoto's plan to
attack Pearl Harbor would be officially
named Operation Z, a name he had chosen
in honor of a famous message known as
the Z signal that Admiral Togo had
conveyed to his men before the Battle of
Toshima. On this one battle rests the
fate of our nation. Let every man do his
utmost. The upcoming attack on Pearl
Harbor, Yamamoto believed, would be of
equal significance. The fate of Japan
hung in the balance. For the attack
itself, Yamamoto planned to use aircraft
carriers to strike the American base. At
a time when most Japanese admirals still
favored traditional naval engagements,
using battleships and other surface
vessels in head-to-head combat, Yamamoto
was one of the first to recognize the
strength of modern naval aviation, the
use of planes at sea, funding and
promoting the construction of a fleet of
10 aircraft carriers by 1941, each of
which could launch over 50 aircraft. The
employment of these carriers would make
the entire operation possible, allowing
the Japanese to launch a devastating air
raid against Pearl Harbor, all while
keeping their own ships at a distance
safe from retaliation. As such, a strike
force of six carriers would be created
to carry out the mission. Known as the
Kido Bhutai, with Vice Admiral Chuichi
Nagumo to serve as its commander. A
seasoned admiral and skilled tactician,
Yamamoto hoped he would have the
experience to execute such a complex
operation. With a commander now
selected, Yamamoto and his team could
turn their attention towards tackling
two significant problems that Operation
Z would have to overcome. The first
would be maintaining the element of
surprise, as approaching Hawaii by
traditional routes would expose the
strike force to discovery by American
patrols and end the operation before it
even began. The second problem would be
that the Japanese carriers did not have
enough fuel capacity to make the journey
in one trip, meaning that they would
have to be refueled at some point along
the route without being discovered.
After much discussion, a plan was
finally formed that looked to solve both
of these problems. The Kido Bhai was to
head to an unexpected and unprolled part
of the ocean 800 m north of Hawaii,
which would be out of range of American
reconnaissance. And with the Americans
expecting that any attack on Pearl
Harbor would likely come from the
Marshall Islands to the west, an attack
from this direction would take them by
complete surprise. Being accompanied by
specialized fuel ships, the carriers
could also solve their second problem by
refueling along the way before
continuing their journey to Pearl Harbor
in complete radio silence to avoid
detection. While taking out the American
fleet at Pearl Harbor was essential, the
true prize were the oil fields of the
Dutch East Indies with a simultaneous
assault to take place against the
Philippines that morning alongside
Malaya, Guam, Wake, Hong Kong, and
Singapore. With the exact timing of
these attacks to be essential if secrecy
was to be maintained, it was to be a
surprise attack of epic proportions. No
longer would the Japanese have to
succumb to the whims and demands of the
European colonial powers. It would be an
Asian continent controlled by Asians
with the Japanese seeing themselves not
as conquerors but rather as liberators
of the Asian
people. With the plan now set, the Kido
Bhutai would be dispatched on November
26th, the very day that the Japanese
received Hull's final note, which they
perceived as little more than a complete
declaration of war. The crew aboard the
carriers, having been kept in the dark
up until this point, would be informed
for the first time that their target was
to be Pearl Harbor, with a great cheer
erupting amongst the young men, for whom
many this would be the first real combat
they would get to engage in. Moving in
radio silence, the ships would turn off
all lights to travel in complete
blackout, with them also taking another
serious precaution, changing the
Japanese fleet code. This would
completely neutralize the American
codereakers who would now be unable to
decipher their messages, leaving both
their plan of attack and whereabouts to
complete mystery. One thing was now for
certain. Wherever the Japanese decided
to attack, the Americans would not see
it coming.
With the Kido Bhutai nearing their
target, the Americans would begin to
prepare for a Japanese attack somewhere
in the Pacific. But where that was was
still anyone's guess. The British had
noted a significant buildup of Japanese
naval forces near the Melee Peninsula
with them relaying this information to
Washington DC on December 6th. Upon
hearing the news during a meeting of the
American naval leadership, Navy
Secretary Frank Knox would ask,
"Gentlemen, are they going to hit us?"
"No, Mr. Secretary," Rear Admiral Turner
would reply, "They are going to hit the
British. They are not ready for us yet."
It was a sentiment shared by much of the
American military who believed Japan to
be either unwilling or incapable of
making an attack against them. If the
Japanese did dare to make an attack,
most thoughts the Philippines was the
most likely target. Would there been
almost no one who seriously believed
that Pearl Harbor was in any sort of
danger? This would be reflected in a
message sent to General Walter C. Short,
the American Army commander responsible
for Pearl Harbor. The message warned him
that the Japanese were likely to strike
somewhere in the Pacific, but had no
indication that Pearl Harbor itself
would be a possible target. instead
ordering him not to take any actions
that were likely to cause panic amongst
the civilian population. As a result,
Sha believed the most serious threat
Pearl Harbor faced was sabotage from the
160,000 Hawaiian residents of Japanese
ancestry. To mitigate this threat, the
island's planes were clustered together
on the runways so they could be more
closely guarded, and military supplies
such as anti-aircraft rounds were locked
away to prevent sabotage. To reinforce
the security of American outposts, he
would send two of the three
USPacific-based aircraft carriers from
Pearl Harbor to Wake and Midway Island,
delivering support aircraft and
reinforcements. The third carrier, the
Saratoga, was undergoing maintenance
back on the west coast of the United
States at the time. This would mean that
the entire US carrier force, the key
target of Yamamoto's operation, would
now be absent at the time of the attack.
[Music]
The Japanese forces attacked Pearl
Harbor on the morning of December 7th,
1941. The attackers achieved complete
surprise with almost every American who
looked up to the sky and saw the
Japanese planes, assuming they were
friendly aircraft engaged in training
exercises. But then the first bombs
exploded. torpedoes specially designed
for shallow waters surrounding the port
as well as armor-piercing bombs which
were dropped above the ships piercing
straight through their decks. Commander
Mitsuo Fida leading the Japanese aerial
forces would message Nagumo Tora tora
translating to tiger tiger tiger letting
his commander know that he had achieved
a strategic operational and tactical
surprise. As more and more planes
arrived overhead, one pilot would take
this photograph of battleship row,
showing the American fleet tightly
grouped together, making them easy
targets for the wave after wave of
Japanese torpedo and dive bombers that
were to come. Within minutes, the
battleships Maryland and Tennessee were
each hit, followed by the Arizona, which
sank almost instantly. The first
Japanese wave consisted of 183 planes
with torpedo bombers attacking the ships
and dive bombers simultaneously
attacking the airfields, preventing
airborne resistance. But much to their
surprise, they found all the US aircraft
clustered together, making them an easy
target. Short's decision to pack them
tightly together to prevent sabotage had
proven to be a costly mistake with the
Japanese dive bombers wiping out almost
all of their planes. The Americans were
also unable to shoot back as their
anti-aircraft ammunition had been locked
away to prevent sabotage. Desperate
attempts were made to fight back with
men resorting to using their pistols to
fire at the bombers as they passed by.
After a brief interval, a second wave of
170 Japanese planes appeared, all of
which were tasked with finishing off the
battleships that were still afloat or
only partially damaged. However, the
Americans were alert this time and
succeeded at shooting down 24 Japanese
planes with only five Japanese planes
having been shot down in the first
attack. 90 minutes later, the attack was
over. The Japanese had sunk or damaged
19 ships and destroyed 188 planes while
damaging 159 others. The attack killed
2,43 US servicemen with nearly half of
them on the US battleship Arizona. It
appeared to be a total victory for
Japan, who had only lost 29 aircraft
during the assault. Admiral Nagumo was
concerned sending a third wave would
open his carriers up to attack, and so
any further strikes were called off,
believing sufficient damage had been
done. However, although Japanese losses
were minuscule, victory was not
complete. The US carrier force,
Yamamoto's key target, was not at Pearl
Harbor, leaving the Americans with one
of the most powerful parts of their navy
still intact. The attack had also failed
to hit American fuel depots and had not
destroyed the US submarine base, leaving
them with resources with which to
rebuild their fleet. The next day,
President Franklin Roosevelt declared
war on the Japanese Empire. And 3 days
later, Germany and Italy declared war on
the United States. Pearl Harbor would
rally the American people who were once
isolationists into a furious nation
intent on revenge. With Americans from
all over the United States, flocking to
recruitment stations, far from wiping
out American influence in the Pacific,
the Japanese had just awoken a sleeping
giant. Yamamoto's biggest fear was about
to come to fruition. A prolonged war
with an industrial superpower was about
to begin.
[Music]